Inventory of the Eritrean subject collection, 1940-2015
Hoover Institution Archives
Eritrean subject collection
1940-2015
XX815
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 sound disc (2.8 linear feet)
Bulletins, pamphlets, press releases, speeches, printed matter, memorabilia, video tape, and sound recording relating to drought and famine in Eritrea, the independence movement led by the Eritrean People's Liberation Front, the establishment of Eritrean independence in 1993, and political, social, and economic conditions in Eritrea.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Bulletins, pamphlets, press releases, speeches, printed matter, memorabilia, video tape, and sound recording relating to drought and famine in Eritrea, the independence movement led by the Eritrean People's Liberation Front, the establishment of Eritrean independence in 1993, and political, social, and economic conditions in Eritrea.
Eritrean People's Liberation Front.; Hezbāwi genbār ḥārenat ʼÉretrā.; Droughts--Eritrea.; Eritrea--Famines.; Eritrea--History.; Nationalism--Eritrea.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Subject File, 1940, 1948, 1966-2015 (Box 1-4)
  - Address by H.E. Isaias Afwerki (Afewerki), 29th OAU Summit, Cairo,", 1993 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - The Atlantic Monthly, "The Loneliest War," by Robert D. Kaplan, 1988 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - "Cooperative Project Within the Archival Sphere Between Eritrea and Switzerland," final report, by Dr. Manz Matthias, 1996 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - "The Eritrea Community-Based Theatre Project," by Jane Plastow, 1996 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Health, 1997 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Information development, "Library Development in Eritrea: A New Struggle in a New Country", by Sandy Macmillen, 1996 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - "A New Beginning in Ethiopia and Eritrea: Guidelines to the Healing of the Land Through a Proper Federal Solution," by Martin Dent, 1990 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - "Proposal for the Establishment of an Eritrean National Archives (ENA)," by Issayas Tesfamariam, 1994 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Referendum in Eritrea, 1993 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Eritrea 1st year anniversary, "Never Kneel Down,", 1992 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - "Eritrea: Revolution Until Victory," ELF Foreign Information Center, postcard, 1979 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - "Freedom and Peace: The Aspiration of Eritrean People," Eritrean People's Liberation Front (EPLF), season's greetings card, 1990 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - "Sahel as Country, EPLF as Government," memories from the North-Eastern Sahel Front on the 30th Anniversary of the Demise of the Wukan Iz (Command), invitation card, 2014 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Satra Traditional Weaving, one business card and one pamphlet, undated (Box-folder 1:14)
  - "September 1st 1991, 30th Anniversary of the Eritrean Peoples Armed Struggle," (Box-folder 1:15)
  - "Brigade 4: Tidy," commemorative paper hat for the 30th anniversary of the demise of Wukaw Iz, 2014 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - "Eritrea May 24th," "Eritrea 1991: Free at Last," "I will see you in Asmara soon," "Eritrea: People's project for a Democratic Constitution," bumper stickers, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Washington Post commentary, "Can Somalia Survive the UN?," by Isaias Afwerki, 1993 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - "African Charter on Human and Civil Rights: This charter was passed in May 1981 by African Leaders on O.A.U.'s 18th conference held in Kenya," produced by the Constitutional Commission of Eritrea, circa 1981 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - "Constitutional Process for Debate," Constitution Commission of Eritrea (CCE), produced for public debate, 1995 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Constitutional Commission of Eritrea (CCE), draft constitution, 1996 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - "Draft Proclamation on the Formation of Political Parties and Organizations,", 2001 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - "Elementary (ABC's) of a Constitution," CCE, 1994 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - "Message of the Constitution Commission of Eritrea,", undated (Box-folder 1:25)
  - "A First Hand Account of Peace Talks between EPLF and the Ethiopian Government," by Saleh Meky, flyer, Africa Table, Stanford University, 1990 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - "An African Affair: Charity Banquet, Fade School Project, Eritrea," with guest speaker Thomas Keneally, author of Schindler's List, 1994 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - "Eritrean Update: The Afar Question/Referendum," with Dr. Roy Pateman, Ecology/Reforestation; Dr. Scott Jones, Women's Role/Psychology; Dr. Belainesh Araia, Economics/History; and Dr. Araia Tseggar, Eritrean and Stanford African Students Association, flyer, 1991 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - "Dawn After a Long Night: The Rebirth of Eritrea," with Dr. Araia Tseggai, Dr. Belainesh Araia, Dr. Roy Pateman and Dr. Scott Jones, Stanford African Students Association of Eritreana, flyer, 1991 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - "Plant Your Love: Help Eritrean Farmers Grow Their Own Food," fundraiser, with speakers Jeanmarie Condon, Dr. Asmarom Legesse, and Testa A. Seyoum, 1989 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - "Share Your Warmth: Isn't It too Hot in Africa for Blankets?," Eritrean Relief Committee (ERC), San Jose, CA branch, 1988 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Application form for Eritrean identity card, 1992 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - "Provisional Government of Eritrea (E.P.L.F.) Application for Entry or Tourist Permit," blank form, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Gazette of Eritrea Laws, "Eritrean Nationality Proclamation No. 21,", 1992 (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Gazette of Eritrean Laws, "Investment Proclamation No. 18,", 1991 (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Gazette of Eritrean Laws, "Investment Proclamation No. 59,", 1994 (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Associazione Italia-Eritrea, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - "30th Anniversary of the Demise of the Wukaw Iz (Command)," "Sahel as Country EPLF as Government by the Holiday Coordinating Committee Zoba," celebration program, 2014 (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Informacao Eritreia by Centro de Informacas e Documentacao Amilcar Cabral, 1980 (Box-folder 1:39)
  - Informational package, "Eritrea: Africa's Newest State,", 1993 (Box-folder 1:40)
  - Information package, "Eritrea: Three Decades of Struggle for Self-Determination," EPLF, 1991 (Box-folder 1:41)
  - "Equality Through Equal Participation in Work," National Union of Eritrean Women, undated (Box-folder 1:42)
  - Geneva Conference on African Refugees, Eritrea, 1981 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - "Eritrea: Healing a Nation and Beyond," International Committee for the Eritrean Blind, 1994 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Basic information on Eritrea, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1991 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Ministry of Information and Culture, 1992 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - United States mission to Eritrea, 1998 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - "War and Famine in Eritrea, Refugees in Sudan," Unitarian Universalist Service Committee, 1985 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Asmara University fact sheet, 1991 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Eritrean Liberation Front Foreign Mission - People's Liberation Forces, Mogadiscio Office, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Eritrea profile, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Eritrea-related news items, 1993 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Nai Ertra Semunawi Gazeta, Eritrea weekly newspaper, 1940 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Hadas Eritrea (New Eritrea), vol. 73, no. 99, 1993, 1996 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - "The Legacy Continues: Eritrea in World Prints,", 1990 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - News items on Eritrea-Ethiopia War, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - "Text of Agreement Between Eritrea and Ethiopia,", 2000 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - "Eritrea Free: A Newsletter of U.S. Committee for a Free Eritrea,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Eritrean Development Foundation (EDF), 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - "Eritrea," monthly newsletter of the Bay Area, 1991 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - "La Lettre de Nakfa," Mensuel publie par le Bureau Central des Relations Exterieures du Front Populaire de Liberation de L'Erythree, 1984 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - "13th Eritrean Book Fair," flyer, 2014 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - "Brigade 44, May 1977-March 1984, Brief History and Poems," pamphlet on the 30th anniversary of the demise of Wukaw Iz, 2014 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - "Eri-TV (Eritrea Television) America's First and Only Eritrean Television Channel," brochure, undated (Box-folder 3:5)
  - "Eritrea: Tre Diverse Stagioni in Due Ore (Eritrea: Three Seasons in Two Hours)," tourism pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 3:6)
  - "The Eritrean Independence Struggle," Eritrean People's Liberation Front: Central Bureau for Foreign Relations, undated (Box-folder 3:7)
  - "Food, Yes!! Bombs, No!!: A Campaign for Food and Peace in Eritrea and Ethiopia,", undated (Box-folder 3:8)
  - "Let's Build Eritrea's National Martyrs Park," pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 3:9)
  - "Memories from Northeastern Sahel Front (1979-1984),", 2014 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - "Referendum: Yes to independence,", 1993 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Research and Information Center of Eritrea (RICE), 1983 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Thirst for Learning Foundation, undated (Box-folder 3:13)
  - "Women Who Are the Main Force of Social Change and Development!," National Union of Eritrean Women, 1988 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - "Young People! Let's Touch the Future Together," Eritrean Relief Committee, 1980s (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Eritrean Liberation Front Revolutionary Council (ELF-RC), International Relations Office, 2001 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Eritrean People's Liberation Front press releases, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - "Draught Disaster Continues in Eritrea: An Urgent Appeal to Humanity," Eritrean Relief Association (ERA), 1983 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Eritrean Relief Committee, Inc. New York, NY, 1983-1993 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Referendum Commission of Eritrea (RCE) press releases, 1993 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Adulis, monthly magazine published by the Central Bureau of Foreign Relations of the Eritrean People's Liberation Front, 1985 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - "Asmara Palace: A Five Star Hotel for the New Millennium,", undated (Box-folder 3:22)
  - "Eri Tour: On the Occasion of the 10th Eritrean Liberation Anniversary,", 2001 (Box-folder 3:33)
  - "Eritrea Art Time: Crossroads of Art in the Horn of Africa," by Alliance Francaise of Asmara, 2011 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - "Primary Healthcare in Rural Eritrea," Eritrean Public Health Program, 1985 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - "Eritrean Relief Association," by Khartoum Sundan, booklet, undated (Box-folder 3:26)
  - "An Exhibition of Art Works by Eritrean Fighters," National Guidance Department, Eritrean People's Liberation Front, 1990 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - "Health Millennium Development Goals Report, Abridged Version: Innovations Driving Health MDG's in Eritrea,", 2014 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - "History of Eritrea from Ancient up to Independence," EPLF educational literature, 2012 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Kensington publication, 1996 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Liberation, monthly publication by the Eritrean People's Liberation Front, Central Bureau of Foreign Relations, 1981 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - "The Mineral Resources and Investment Opportunities in Eritrea," Ministry of Energy, Mills and Water Resources, 1995 (Box-folder 3:32)
  - "Mekeyero/Game Changer: Stories from the Experiences of Gedhi (fighter for Eritrean Independence)," no. 2, 2014 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - "The National Insurance Corporation of Eritrea (N.I.C.E): Offering Eritreans an Investment Opportunity to Participate in the Government Privatization,", 2004 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - "Participants of the Fighters War 1984," by Colonel Gebreigz'dbiher Menau, 2013 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - "A Research That Looked into the Condition of Women," by Research and Information Department of the National Union of Eritrean Women, 1999 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Sagem, monthly publication of Eritrean People's Liberation Front, no. 3, 1987 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - "Sahel: The Enemy's Graveyard, Brief History of the EPLF and the Various Offensives by the Ethiopian Forces,", 2014 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - "Special Issue Prepared by the National Holidays Coordinating Committee on the Occasion of the Fifth Independence Anniversary,", 1996 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - "State, Government, Party," by Provisional Government of Eritrea, 1992 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - "Treaty on the Rights of Children," passed by the UN General Assembly, 1989 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - "UN General Assembly Resolution 2263: Proclamation to Prevent Discrimination Against Women,", 1967 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - "UN Resolution on Rights of the Public Towards Peace Passed by the General Assembly,", 1984 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - "UNESCO Proclamation on Universal Understanding of Cultural Exchange. Proclamation on the Structures of Progress,", 1966 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - "Universal Declaration of Human Rights," "International Treaty on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights," "International Treaty on Civil and Political Rights," as passed, described, and explained by UN General Assembly Decision, 1948 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - "Voice of Eritrean Women," National Union of Eritrean Women, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - "Women in Traditional Eritrean Society, Part One," by National Union of Eritrean Women, 1999 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - "Women in Traditional Eritrean Society, Part Two," by National Union of Eritrean Women, 1999 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - "To Commemorate the Days of Referendum in Eritrea," postage stamps, 1993 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - "Yes"/"No" referendum ballots, 1993 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - "The Referendum Bulletin," Referendum Commission of Eritrea (RCE), 1993 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - "Special Report on Eritrea," Eritrean Relief Association (ERA) Canada, 1992 (Box-folder 4:20)
  - "Summary Report: The 3rd Congress of the National Union of Eritrean Women,", 1988 (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Statement by H.E. Mr. Isaias Afwerki at the 48th Session of the United Nations General Assembly, New York, 1993 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - "20th Anniversary of National Union of Eritrean Women 1979-1999," calendar (Box-folder 4:23)
  - 35th anniversary of NUEW, Women's Day, 2015 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Agezo, special issue, "20 Years in Struggle and Resistance," on the 20th anniversary of the founding of National Union of Eritrean Women, 1999 (Box-folder 4:25)
  - "Constitution of the National Union of Eritrean Women,", 1998 (Box-folder 4:25)
  - "The State of Eritrea Postal Service: 20th Anniversary of National Union of Eritrean Women," postage and postcard, 2000 (Box-folder 4:26)
  - "National Union of Eritrean Youth (NUEY). Experiences and Horizons,", 1994 (Box-folder 4:27)
  - Resistance, bimonthly newsletters of National Union of Eritrean Students, 1980 (Box-folder 4:28)
- Memorabilia and Videorecording, 2003, 2014, undated (Box 5-6)
  - Eritrean flags (3), undated (Box 5)
  - "Shida," a plastic sandal worn by Eritrean People's Liberation Front (EPLF) fighters, undated (Box 5)
  - Referendum Commission of Eritrea hat, undated (Box 5)
  - Eritrea flag placemat and Eritrean map placemat, undated (Box 5)
  - "Eritrea 2000: Under the Sycamore Tree and More," 1 videocassette (VHS), 2003 (Box 5)
  - Martyrs Memorial, 5 pins, undated (Box 6)
  - "Eritrea Is Free," keyholder, undated (Box 6)
  - EPLF emblem and Eritrean flag shoulder badges, undated (Box 6)
  - "Sahel as a Country, EPLF as a Government: 30th Anniversary of the Demise of Wukaw Iz," tote bag, 2014 (Box 6)
- Sound Recording, 1980
  - "Chants et Danses d'Erythree (Songs and Dances of Eritrea) and Eritrean Revolutionary Songs," sound disc (Record-cabinet cabinet)
    Scope and Contents note
    Track A1, "The Eritrea People Is Wall"
    Track A2, "The Flame of the Fight to Extend"
    Track A3, "After Retreat"
    Track A4, "Our Red Sea"
    Track B1, "Layeye Lale Lalena"
    Track B2, "Eritrea Ba Ba"
    Track B3, "Ana Sefalelku"
    Track B4, "Our Popular Army"
    Track B5, "Never Go Back After a Challenge"